<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Edgard Minete</title>
    <link>https://edgmin.github.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://edgmin.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://edgmin.github.io/media/icon_hua2b1b6d47a67b4a2c33931043b472208_26072_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.PNG</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://edgmin.github.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Domain Adaptation - Taxonomy and New Methods</title>
      <link>https://edgmin.github.io/post/masters/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://edgmin.github.io/post/masters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post, I would like to talk a bit about the work I developed during my master&amp;rsquo;s thesis at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cvai.in.tum.de/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Computer Vision &amp;amp; Artificial Intelligence Group&lt;/a&gt; of the Technical University of Munich, under the supervision of &lt;a href=&#34;https://vision.in.tum.de/members/golkov&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Vladimir Golkov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, I believe it is worth explaining how I ended up writing my master&amp;rsquo;s thesis at TU Munich, since I was pursuing my studies at TU Braunschweig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;What lies ahead? Image credit: &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/K2u71wv2eI4&amp;#34; target=&amp;#34;_blank&amp;#34; rel=&amp;#34;noopener&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Unsplash&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/masters/back_head_hucdb173c52266abd73a3e5f72ca9b44e7_2187159_9d956ce347f2f7d15cb49bc1b3016bcb.webp 400w,
               /post/masters/back_head_hucdb173c52266abd73a3e5f72ca9b44e7_2187159_fc884cad260072c9e773c1e655e18037.webp 760w,
               /post/masters/back_head_hucdb173c52266abd73a3e5f72ca9b44e7_2187159_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://edgmin.github.io/post/masters/back_head_hucdb173c52266abd73a3e5f72ca9b44e7_2187159_9d956ce347f2f7d15cb49bc1b3016bcb.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was planning/looking for a master&amp;rsquo;s thesis topic, I could not really find anything that got my attention at TU Braunschweig. Then, I decided to look around and, after a few days and emails, I was fortunate to get to know Dr. Golkov from TU Munich. As I planned to learn the behind the scenes of deep learning, before accepting to write my master&amp;rsquo;s thesis at TU Munich I asked Vladimir about the potential topics I could work on. He offered me a range of topics, but one of them really stood out in the crowd: understanding deep learning. That was instantly a match for me, as I was definitely searching for something to comprehensively understand deep learning and its concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a year reading hundreds of papers, having tons of fruitful discussions, and constantly coding, I successfully presented my master&amp;rsquo;s thesis at TU Braunschweig. Though still an ongoing work, below I present a draft of it with some discussion for those who might be interested. An article on arXiv will also appear soon 😄.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading-1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading-2&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading-3&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading-4&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading-5&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-efficiency-in-deep-learning&#34;&gt;Data-efficiency in deep learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deep learning-based methods rely on many strategies to achieve data-efficiency. One of the most common techniques is to endow models with prior knowledge about the underlying problem by using neural network layers with purposefully tailored properties. This approach lies at the heart of deep learning, but is quite often overlooked by machine learning practitioners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at the prominent example of convolutional neural networks (CNNs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CNNs are empowered with convolutional and pooling layers, which leverage them with translation equivariance and scale separation capabilities (not to mention the deep natural image initialization prior - but that&amp;rsquo;s worth another post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Convolutional neural network. Image credit: &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#34;https://medium.com/swlh/an-overview-on-convolutional-neural-networks-ea48e76fb186&amp;#34; target=&amp;#34;_blank&amp;#34; rel=&amp;#34;noopener&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Medium&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/masters/cnns_huf86549c46500d4eb201f0cae6f4fca78_56387_852426294e0e4b7ec21258493b8b5cd7.webp 400w,
               /post/masters/cnns_huf86549c46500d4eb201f0cae6f4fca78_56387_1e5cd0c0577948f3f8379d23fbfb7007.webp 760w,
               /post/masters/cnns_huf86549c46500d4eb201f0cae6f4fca78_56387_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://edgmin.github.io/post/masters/cnns_huf86549c46500d4eb201f0cae6f4fca78_56387_852426294e0e4b7ec21258493b8b5cd7.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;253&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These aspects of CNNs are essentially what make them shine, as they substantially reduce the number of parameters, the associated computational cost, and the amount of data needed for training. Interestingly (and perhaps unnoticed by many), at a more macroscopic level, certain architectural design and training strategies are also known to greatly benefit neural networks&amp;rsquo; performance. These strategies can be very diverse and range from a simple cluster assumption to more complex concepts such as adversarial learning. However, there is one interesting difference. Namely, there is evidence that the latter strategies pose a more abstract power, being transferable across different data types and tasks. The problem is that there are neither guidelines about when using such strategies is beneficial, nor clear explanations about how they help to solve issues in deep learning approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;deep-domain-adaptation-taxonomy-and-new-methods&#34;&gt;Deep Domain Adaptation: Taxonomy and New Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my master&amp;rsquo;s thesis, I researched about design strategies (patterns) and tried to understand the context in which they are employed and what problems they try to solve. In other words, I investigated task- and data-agnostic architectural design patterns for recurring problems in deep learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the analysis, I used an existing &amp;ldquo;visual language&amp;rdquo; of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cvai.in.tum.de/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Computer Vision &amp;amp; Artificial Intelligence Group&lt;/a&gt;. The idea behind this visual language is to abstract out neural networks&amp;rsquo; topological details, such as type and number of layers, and therefore to provide a common language to analyze deep learning methods. By bringing diverse methods under the same umbrella, I could identify more than 20 design patterns employed throughout deep learning. Furthermore, to understand the machine learning scenario in which each design pattern is commonly employed, I proposed an ontology of machine learning tasks. Combining the list of design patterns and the ontology of machine learning tasks, a methodology for a more structured design of novel deep learning approaches was possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a proof of concept of the proposed methodology, I extended an existing unsupervised (self-supervised contrastive) deep domain adaptation approach by injecting design patterns into it. Interestingly, the changes leveraged state-of-the-art performance on the popular and challenging &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.06924&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;VisDA-2017&lt;/a&gt; domain adaptation benchmark, providing empirical evidence that design patterns are interchangeable across distinct machine learning tasks and data types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I am still working on this topic and doing additional experiments. Nonetheless, I am confident that the proposed methodology will be the starting point of a more structured analysis of deep learning approaches, and that it will provide guidelines for the design of novel deep learning approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A paper about it is expected to be released soon. So, be tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Multidisciplinary Journey</title>
      <link>https://edgmin.github.io/post/journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://edgmin.github.io/post/journey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As this is the first post of my personal blog, it couldn&amp;rsquo;t be different: today I will write a bit about my academic and professional journey!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began my studies back in 2009, when I started a technical course in mechanics at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ifes.edu.br/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Federal Institute of Espírito Santo&lt;/a&gt;, Brazil. In this course, I was exposed to a range of topics including mechanical projects, electronics, mechanical fabrication, metrology, materials science and beyond. The course was half-half theory and practice. Thereby, I also acquired some hands-on experience. Further, I had the opportunity to lead the welding lab practices for a cohort of about 20 students during one semester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2010, I was fortunate to be admitted to the main university of my state, &lt;a href=&#34;https://internacional.ufes.br/en/home&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UFES&lt;/a&gt;, in the undergraduate course of Mechanical Engineering. Simultaneously, I started to learn the English and German languages, as I was planning to one day study abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2011, the Brazilian government launched the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.br/cnpq/pt-br/acesso-a-informacao/acoes-e-programas/programas/ciencia-sem-fronteiras&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Science Without Boarders - CSF&lt;/a&gt; exchange program, which gave the opportunity to outstanding students to have experiences abroad by providing them with scholarships. As I was already learning foreign languages and had good grades in my undergraduate studies, I could meet the admission requirements and I was offered a scholarship to study in Germany.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;One of the first days in Germany at a shopping mall in Dresden&amp;lt;a href=&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/journey/dresden_hu8f0d9c0aed59f71f5cceaa03971b1c06_142503_bbe959a4a3da3b4fedda9adcd5e50f1a.webp 400w,
               /post/journey/dresden_hu8f0d9c0aed59f71f5cceaa03971b1c06_142503_f225b98e6cf54094751abf4fc9bae72b.webp 760w,
               /post/journey/dresden_hu8f0d9c0aed59f71f5cceaa03971b1c06_142503_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://edgmin.github.io/post/journey/dresden_hu8f0d9c0aed59f71f5cceaa03971b1c06_142503_bbe959a4a3da3b4fedda9adcd5e50f1a.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;683&#34;
               height=&#34;554&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2013, I moved to Dresden, Germany, to then start my exchange program. There, I lived for 3 months and participated in intensive German culture and language courses. After this adaptation period, I moved to the city of Zwickau, where I participated in the Automotive Engineering and Management course as an exchange master student. During the course, I had the opportunity to gain general knowledge about the automotive industry, such as motor development, acoustics, logistics and beyond. Importantly, I also had my first experiences with simulation sciences (in particular computational fluid dynamics), which rapidly increased my interest in the field. Besides that, I did an internship at Audi AG on the resistance welding development team between 2014 and 2015. There, I learned more about the German labor market, vividly experienced the German culture, and gained knowledge of robotic welding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;First day of my internship at Audi AG &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#34;_&amp;#34;&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/journey/audi_hu312d9d3611ca038e3e6b1e8d68452614_465391_1233293a76424c3ef17275a78d482911.webp 400w,
               /post/journey/audi_hu312d9d3611ca038e3e6b1e8d68452614_465391_41be8ce20fd362f620f5e3d0a6e21aff.webp 760w,
               /post/journey/audi_hu312d9d3611ca038e3e6b1e8d68452614_465391_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://edgmin.github.io/post/journey/audi_hu312d9d3611ca038e3e6b1e8d68452614_465391_1233293a76424c3ef17275a78d482911.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;549&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the internship at Audi AG, I moved back to Brazil to finish my undergraduate studies in Mechanical Engineering. Simultaneously, I did an internship in a local company (Tecvix), where I was responsible for performing mechanical and fluid dynamics simulations for diverse projects in the oil and gas industry. These simulation experiences, together with the similar experiences I had in Germany, directly influenced my decision to further expand my knowledge in the direction of computational sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After concluding the undergraduate course in Mechanical Engineering in the middle of 2017, I was fortunate to be admitted to the master in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tu-braunschweig.de/en/cse&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Computational Sciences in Engineering&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tu-braunschweig.de/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Technical University of Braunschweig&lt;/a&gt;. During my masters&amp;rsquo; studies, I chose the specialization in Mathematics and Computer Science, but I also took diverse lectures in fluid dynamics. Simultaneously with the theoretical lectures, I sought to improve my research abilities. Therefore, I worked as a research assistant in two different research institutes for more than 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Undergraduate cerimony &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#34;_&amp;#34;&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/journey/bachelors_hu4074748c5bc79a349df7588655202481_115755_703a5dfa9223206c82eca8d58cb02bfa.webp 400w,
               /post/journey/bachelors_hu4074748c5bc79a349df7588655202481_115755_8eda8f211ceec2ae3f29db7c3c97691d.webp 760w,
               /post/journey/bachelors_hu4074748c5bc79a349df7588655202481_115755_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://edgmin.github.io/post/journey/bachelors_hu4074748c5bc79a349df7588655202481_115755_703a5dfa9223206c82eca8d58cb02bfa.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tu-braunschweig.de/en/ifn/institute/dept/sv&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Institute for Communications Technology&lt;/a&gt;, I worked on projects related to the robustness of semantic segmentation deep neural networks (DNNs) under the supervision of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tu-braunschweig.de/en/ifn/institute/team/sv/baer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Andreas Bär&lt;/a&gt;. Among others, the tasks I contributed include: improving an existing approach for domain mismatch estimation by means of multi-task learning and autoencoders; implementing a teacher-student framework for semantic segmentation; and implementing a PyTorch-based &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ifnspaml/TUBSRobustCheck&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;toolbox&lt;/a&gt; to assess the robustness of semantic segmentation DNNs against diverse adversarial attacks and corruptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I also worked as a research assistant at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tu-braunschweig.de/en/fmb/institute-fk4/institutes/institute-of-joining-and-welding&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Institute of Joining and Welding&lt;/a&gt;. There, I had further hands-on experience in simulation sciences and machine learning by working on diverse weld-related projects. My activities there included: development of a differential geometry-based tool to assess porosity properties in welded specimens using 3D computed tomography data; implementation of a ResNet-based data-efficient neural network for the prediction of stress-strain curve of welded alloys using multi-fidelity (2D/3D simulation and experimental) depth-indentation testing data; execution of multi-focal laser welding thermal simulations for welding parameter estimation; and developed a weld bead image segmentation tool to automatically segment and measure weld beads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;An excursion day during my master&amp;amp;rsquo;s studies &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#34;_&amp;#34;&amp;gt;_&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/journey/cse_hu266863908cf2fd53416034f90ff76061_939747_d4c3259c23bbd95c2da16a444a9ab802.webp 400w,
               /post/journey/cse_hu266863908cf2fd53416034f90ff76061_939747_6086d769280749c94ea0a25e16eb640d.webp 760w,
               /post/journey/cse_hu266863908cf2fd53416034f90ff76061_939747_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://edgmin.github.io/post/journey/cse_hu266863908cf2fd53416034f90ff76061_939747_d4c3259c23bbd95c2da16a444a9ab802.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;459&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, I wrote my masters thesis at the Technical University of Munich where I was supervised by &lt;a href=&#34;https://vision.in.tum.de/members/golkov&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Vladimir Golkov&lt;/a&gt; and worked on topics around understanding of deep learning, self-supervised learning, and unsupervised deep domain adaptation. If you are interested in reading more about my master&amp;rsquo;s thesis, please take a look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://edgmin.github.io/post/masters/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude, I would like to share my research interests: I am interested in developing autonomous (also aerial) vehicles. In particular, I would like to research about data-efficient methods to improve robotic perception and planning by exploiting strategies such as self-supervised/unsupervised learning, transfer learning, etc. Further, I am also excited about endowing deep learning algorithms with strong learning biases/regularizers to give them the ability to better understand the complex world around us.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
